Bellow players, I'm sorry to be the one
to break it to you, but this is not an
infinite combo. You can't play Bellow,
then Greater Good, then sacrifice
Enduring Courage, thinking that when it
comes back, thanks to its ability,
Bellow will make it a creature again, so
you can sacrifice it to the greater good
and draw through your entire deck. And
look, you can't blame me. You got to
blame layers and timestamps. Let me
explain. So, for those new, let's
quickly break down the cards. Bellow
Bard of Brambles is a gr three mana 33
that says, "During your turn, each
non-equipment artifact and non-ora
enchantment you control with mana value
four or greater is a 44 elemental
creature in addition to its other types
and has indestructible haste. And
whenever this creature deals combat
damage to a player, draw a card.
Enduring Courage is a red four mana 33
enchantment creature that says whenever
another creature you control enters it
gets plus two plus O and gains haste
until the end of turn. And when Enduring
Courage dies, if it was a creature,
return it to the battlefield under its
owner's control. It's an enchantment.
This is the important part right here.
And finally, Greater Good is a four mana
enchantment that says, "Sacrifice a
creature. draw cards equal to the
sacrifice creature's power, then discard
three cards. So again, the idea is you
have these three cards in play. Bellow
makes enduring courage a 44. You
sacrifice the courage to greater good to
draw four and discard three. And then
Enduring Courage comes back into play as
an enchantment. Bellow then turns
Enduring Courage into a creature again.
So you can then repeat this loop. But
again, for clarity's sake, this does not
work like this. If you've seen my
previous video about Bellow and the
Theos gods, you might have an idea about
what's going to actually happen here.
And if you'd like to test your rules
knowledge, pause the video now and see
if you can explain what the issue is
here in the comments.
So, both Bellow's ability and Enduring
Courage's ability apply continuous
effects. And yes, technically Enduring
Courage's abilities are triggered
abilities that then apply a continuous
effect.
Anything that would change the printed
information on a card is considered to
be a continuous effect. So because of
that, we have to head on over to section
613 of the comprehensive rules
interaction of continuous effects.
Now the thing to know with continuous
effects is that when we have multiple of
them in play, we apply them in a
specific order. This is known as the
layers system. We always apply
continuous effects in order of the
layers list top to bottom. These effects
are checked and applied constantly and
instantly. Anytime something happens,
the layers are rechecked and reapplied.
Now for Bellow, their effect applies
across multiple layers. They change
types, which is layer four. They grant
abilities, which is layer six, and they
set power and toughness, which is layer
7B. For enduring courage, their first
ability applies in layer 7 C. Not that
that's relevant for this example. And
their last ability applies in layer 4.
So now we know this bit of information.
Let's run through the example again. We
have bellow, enduring courage, and
greater good in play. Enduring courage
hasn't died yet, so their last ability
hasn't come into play yet. So, let's
apply the layers. Going through the list
in order, Bellow's effect starts at
layer four. So, we'll make greater good
and enduring courage creatures with the
elemental subtype. We will then move to
layer six where Bellow then grants these
creatures indestructible haste. And
whenever this creature deals combat
damage to a player, draw a card. And
finally, they set their power and
toughness to 44 in layer seven. Okay,
nice and easy so far. Next, let's
sacrifice the good boy to greater good.
We'll get a greater good trigger and an
enduring courage trigger. Let's resolve
those. And we'll resolve Enduring
Courage's trigger. As it was a creature,
we can return it to the battlefield
under its owner's control. However, once
it's back on the battlefield, it's an
enchantment and as the reminder text
says, not a creature. Now, remember
this, it's an enchantment and not a
creature effect is a continuous effect.
Anything that changes the printed text
on a card by adding or removing or
changing anything is a continuous
effect. And as I mentioned before,
anytime anything happens, layers are
checked and applied. So let's do that
now. We'll start at layer 4 and look to
apply Bellow's type changing ability.
But hang on. Enduring courage's effect
also applies at layer 4. It wants to
remove Enduring Courage's creature type
and make them just an enchantment. So
what do we do in this situation? Which
order do we apply them in? You may have
heard me talk about these before. This
is where we look at timestamps. When we
have two effects on the same layer
wanting to apply, we apply them in time
stamp order. Whichever effect has the
older time stamp gets applied first.
Bellow's ability time stamp is tied to
Bellow itself thanks to rule 613.7A.
A continuous effect generated by a
static ability has the same time stamp
as the object the static ability is on
or the timestamp of the effect that
created the ability whichever is later.
And Bella received their time stamp when
they entered play thanks to rule 613.7D.
An object receives a time stamp at the
time it enters a zone. So for clarity,
we'll say Bellow has timestamp number
one. Now, for Enduring Courage, they
themselves would get a new time stamp
when they returned to the battlefield.
However, we're looking specifically at
the time stamp for the it's an
enchantment and not a creature effect.
Rule 613.7b
says a continuous effect generated by
the resolution of a spell or ability
receives a time stamp at the time it's
created. So, to keep things simple,
we'll call this timestamp time stamp
number two.
In this situation, we would apply
Bellow's effect first as it has the
earlier time stamp. Now that we've got
that cleared up, let's go back and try
to apply the layers again. We'll start
at layer 4 and look to apply Bellow's
type-changing ability and enduring
couri's effect. This time, we know we
apply them in time stamp order. So, we
apply Bellow's effect first, then we
apply Enduring Courage's effect. Now,
this is the part that tripped me up.
What does is an enchantment actually
mean here? Initially, I thought this
combo should work because Bellow gives
Enduring Courage the creature type and
simply being an enchantment shouldn't
make any further changes. Cards like
sugarcoat explicitly say is an X and
loses all other card types. So, I
assumed that meant Enduring Courage
would continue being a creature thanks
to Bellow. However, as I'll tell you
time and time again, reading the card
doesn't always explain the card. Rule
205.1A
states, "Some effects set an object's
card type. In most such cases, the new
card type replaces any existing card
types." What this effectively means is
that when Enduring Courage says it's an
enchantment, it means it's an
enchantment and loses all other card
types. So, all that to say that Bellow
makes enduring courage a creature.
Technically, they're already a creature
at this point as their other effect
hasn't been applied yet. Then, Enduring
Courage's effect kicks in and changes
Enduring Courage back to just an
enchantment. It gets rid of the creature
type completely.
We'll continue to apply the rest of the
layers abilities gets applied in layer
six. So, greater good will gain
indestructible haste. And whenever this
creature deals combat damage to a
player, draw a card. And then finally,
we'll apply layer 7B and set Greater
Good's power and toughness to 44. So
that leaves us with a 44 elemental
greater good creature and a purely
enchantment version of Enduring Courage.
So because Enduring Courage is no longer
a creature, you cannot sacrifice it to
greater good, thereby preventing the
infinite loop. It's probably worth
noting that at this point, if you can
find a way to flick a bellow with
something like Sword of Hearth and Home,
Conjurer's Closet, or any other way to
make them change zones, or turn them
face down and face back up again,
they'll get a new time stamp, meaning
they'll have a later time stamp than the
enchantment version of Enduring Courage.
So when the layers get applied, Bellow's
effect will be applied after enduring
couragees it's an enchantment. So Bellow
will turn Enduring Courage back into a
creature.
Now if you want to learn more about
layers, check out this video. And as
always, be sure to give this video
you're watching a like if you learned
something and subscribe because if you
don't, I won't tell Enduring Courage
they're a good boy. Thanks for watching
and I'll see you in the next one.